Register of the James Conrad Myers letters
Hoover Institution Archives
James Conrad Myers letters
1943-1949
96013
Hoover Institution Archives
3 manuscript boxes (1.3 linear feet)
Letters to family members relating to American military operations in China and India during World War II.
Myers, James Conrad, 1924-1986.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1996.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1924 October 10 Born in Anaheim, California
1943 June 15 Graduated from Withrow High School, Cincinnati, Ohio
1943 July - December Stationed at Camp Callan, California
1944 January - March Stationed at Fort Ord, California
1944 March 5 Deployed to Pacific Theater out of Long Beach, California; ports of call included Perth, Australia and Colombo, Ceylon (Sri Lanka)
1944 March - May Stationed at Camp Angus (Calcutta, India) as Army private
1944 May 29 Transferred to Kunming Province, China, as a radio operator with the 993rd Signal Service Company
1944 May - December Stationed in Kunming Province, China, and various parts of the Indo-China border
1944 December Promoted to Technician 5 with the 245th Signal Operation Company, China Combat Command
1945 January - October Stationed in various provinces along the Indo-China border, including 2 months with the 18th Army Division
1945 October Relieved of duty; departed from Calcutta, India, to return to the U.S.
1945 December 30 Returned to his hometown near Cincinnati, Ohio, as a civilian
1949 Married Elna (maiden name unknown)
1986 September 14 Died in Burlingame, California
Scope and Content of Collection
The James Conrad Myers letters consist of letters (accompanied by cartoons, sketches, and portraits in pencil and water color of Myers, acquaintances, and various locations), postcards, a photograph, and clippings related to American military operations in China and India during World War II. Also includes a copy of a memo from Japanese General Yasuji Okamura to Generalissimo Chiang Kai-shek on negotiations for the surrender of Japanese forces in China on August 17, 1945.
The majority of the letters in the collection are to Myers' parents and detail his daily routine as a radio operator and Technician 5 with the 993rd Signal Service Company along the Indo-China border. While he does not describe any combat experience in his letters, Myers does give detailed accounts of base operations. He also includes a number of sketches and illustrations of his travels, as well as portraits of relatives and acquaintances back home. The collection is notable for its level of detail and fullness, and it contains nearly one letter for every month of the war from July 1943 to December 1945.
United States. Army. Signal Service Company, 993rd.; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--China.; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--India.
- Biographical File, 1943
  - High school commencement announcement, 1943 June 15 (Box-folder 1: 1)
- Correspondence, 1943-1949
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains letters from Myers to general recipients (neighbors, female correspondents), his parents, and other family members. Letters cover Myers' basic training in California in 1943 through his deployment and return home to Cincinnati in 1945. The series also includes a letter from Myers to his parents announcing his wedding plans in 1949.
  - Sent, 1943-1949
    - General, 1944-1945
      - 1944 August, October (Box-folder 1: 2-3)
      - 1945 June (Box-folder 1: 4)
      - Undated (Box-folder 1: 5)
    - Parents, 1943-1949
      - 1943 July-December (Box-folder 1: 6-10)
      - 1944 (Box-folder 1: 11-17, 2: 1-5)
      - 1945 (Box-folder 2: 6-14, 3: 1-3)
      - 1949 August (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - Received, 1945 (Box-folder 3: 5)
- Collected Correspondence, 1945
  Contains letters from Myers' sister, Jean, and brother, Gene (Eugene), to their parents. Both individuals describe their travels during the war, as well as their post-war plans. Also contains copy of a memo from Japanese General Yasuji Okamura to Generalissimo Chiang Kai-shek on negotiations for the surrender of Japanese troops in China, dated 1945 August 17.
  - Letters, 1945 June-August (Box-folder 3: 6-8)
  - Memo, 1945 August (Box-folder 3: 9)
- Printed Matter, undated
  - Clipping, undated (Box-folder 3: 10)
    News clipping of "Birds of a Feather" from "The Sad Sack" cartoon series by Sergeant George Baker, circa 1943-1945.
- Photograph, undated
  - James Conrad Myers in uniform, undated (Box-folder 3: 11)